Guide to the Ruth Pine Furniss Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ruth Pine Furniss papers
1919-1960
YCAL MSS 431
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.5
(2 boxes)
The Papers contain writings and other papers of American author Ruth Pine Furniss. Furniss's writings drew on her struggle with mental illness and her exposure to various medical treatments. Her career as an author is documented in various material, including drafts, printed versions of her writings, contracts with publishers, and copyright records. Some of her poetry, short stories, and articles written in the 1920s, and largely published in magazines and newspapers, are in a scrapbook of clippings. Reception of Furniss's novels, including Gay, Snow, and The Layman Looks at Doctors, is documented in reviews gathered into two scrapbooks. The Papers also include a draft for The Dreamland Tree, an unpublished novel completed in 1952. The correspondence of Furniss's son, W. Todd Furniss, reveal his endeavor to have The Dreamland Tree published following his mother's death.
Furniss, Ruth Pine, 1893-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of W. Todd Furniss (Yale 1942), 1983.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ruth Pine Furniss (1893-1957)
Ruth Kellogg Pine Furniss was born on March 2, 1893 to Charles LeRoy and Grace Eddy Kellogg Pine in Lansingburg, New York. She attended the Emma Willard School (Troy, New York) and Miss Porter's School (Farmington, Connecticut). She studied short story writing with Dr. Blanche Colton Williams at Columbia University and went on to publish a number of short stories and novels.
It is believed Furniss suffered from manic-depression, which was treated through periods of institutionalization, shock-therapy, a topectomy, and ultimately, a lobotomy. Furniss's writings drew on her struggle with mental illness and her exposure to various medical treatments, as can be seen in her novels Gay (1928) and Snow (1929), and The Dreamland Tree (completed in 1952 after Furniss received a topectomy and shock therapy). Furniss published The Layman Looks at Doctors (1929) under the pseudonyms S.W. and J.T. Pierce, who were a fictional couple.
In 1912 Furniss married Dr. Henry Dawson Furniss (d. 1942), with whom she had five children, three of whom survived childhood (Henry Dawson, Junior; James P.; and W. Todd). The Furniss family lived in Pelham, New York and New York City. During World War II Furniss served as a Gray Lady with the Red Cross. Furniss was hospitalized at several points during her life for what may have been manic-depression. At the end of her life she was hospitalized at Pilgrim State and Central Islip (Long Island). Furniss died of a heart attack in December 1957 at the age of 64.
Scope and Contents
The Papers contain writings and other papers of American author Ruth Pine Furniss. Furniss's career as an author is documented in various material, including drafts, printed versions of her writings, contracts with publishers, and copyright cards. Some of Furniss's poetry, short stories, and articles written in the 1920s, and largely published in magazines and newspapers, are in a scrapbook of clippings. Reception of Furniss's novels, including Gay, Snow, and The Layman Looks at Doctors, is documented in reviews gathered into two scrapbooks. The Papers also include a draft for The Dreamland Tree, an unpublished novel completed in 1952 close to the end of Furniss's life. The correspondence of Furniss's son, W. Todd Furniss, reveal his endeavor to have The Dreamland Tree published following his mother's death.
The Papers also include personal effects, such as calling cards and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. W. Todd Furniss Correspondence, 1958-1960; II. Writings, 1926-1952; and III. Other Papers, 1919-1940.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Literature and mental illness; Mental illness -- Fiction; Mental illness in literature; Scrapbooks; Furniss, Ruth Pine, 1893-1957; Furniss, W. Todd (Warren Todd), 1921-
- W. Todd Furniss Correspondence, 1958-1960; . I.; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence contains letters between Furniss's son (W. Todd Furniss) and various individuals in relation to his endeavor to have The Dreamland Tree published posthumously. Some of Furniss's correspondence can be found in her "Scrapbook of reviews and correspondence" (Series III).
  - Amster, Leonard, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Harcourt, Brace, and Co., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Menninger Foundation, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scherman, Bernadine, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University Microfilm, Inc., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1926-1952, undated; Series II
  The series is organized into two subseries: Major Works and Articles. Furniss's writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
  Writings consists of drafts and printed versions of Furniss's writings. Printed versions and reviews of Furniss's writings can also be found in Furniss's scrapbooks (Series III).
  - Major Works
    - The Dreamland Tree, typescript, carbon, circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Foreward by W. Todd Furniss for The Dreamland Tree, typescript, carbon, circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Tear-Test: A One-Act Comedy in Two Scenes," typescript, carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles
    - "Notes on Apprenticeship," printed version, The Editor, Vol. 73, No. 9, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The Second Shall Be First," printed version, The Editor, Vol. 82, No. 11, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Other Papers, 1919-1940; Series III
  The series contains documents relating to Furniss's writing career, including scrapbooks, contracts, and copyright cards, as well as personal items such as callings cards and photographs.
  - Scrapbook of reviews and correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook of writings and reviews, 1921-1930
    Contains poems, short stories, articles, and reviews. Short stories include: "Sentence" ( Charm, December, 1924); "Only Once" ( The New Eve, April, 1926); "Relax" ( Chicago Sunday Tribune, May 9, 1926); "Clay" ( Transition, August, 1927); "Bess Does Her Best" ( Chicago Sunday Tribune, November 27, 1927); "Answer" ( Transition, September, 1929); "Triangle" ( Harper's Bazaar, July, 1930); and "Bess gør sit bedste" ( Søndags B.T., October 12, 1930).
  - Contracts and agreements, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Copyright cards, 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Ruth Pine Furniss and W. Todd Furniss, 1919-1922, undated
- Oversize, 1.08; (1 box)
  - Scrapbook of writings and reviews, 1921-1930 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Ruth Pine Furniss and W. Todd Furniss, 1919-1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)